- Hi, it's me, Tim Dodd,
the Everyday Astronaut.
Welcome back to Starbase Texas.
This is of course, where
SpaceX is building their
Starship vehicles.
This is part one of two parts,
and part one, we're gonna
take you around the factory,
see what's new, see the
ships, see the boosters,
see star factory from the
inside for the first time,
and just learn a lot along the way.
So stay tuned for part two
where we'll take you out
to the launchpad and we'll
also follow up with Elon
after the launch and see how it went.
So without further ado,
let's go on another tour with Elon Musk.
Cool. So yeah, as we were
saying, I mean, obviously a,
a lot has changed in
the last couple years.
I mean, [It Has?] this all maybe in
theory, I don't know, I mean,
- Looks exactly the same.
It hasn't changed a bit,
- But once was tents is now
a permanent looking factory.
- Yeah. It used to be intense in tents,
and now it's in a building.
Yeah. Yeah. So we've got this, I think,
pretty good looking
rocket factory building
that we've almost completed.
Completed the exterior.
This is, this will enable us
to have serialized production
of the rocket, especially the ship,
which would ultimately be made, you know,
long term probably be making
a thousand a year of the ship.
So, thousand a year. Yeah.
Well, you know, gotta
build a city on Mars. Yeah.
- That's insane to think about.
- Yeah, I don't, I mean, we
may not build a thousand year
right here, but I think this is,
this is capable of a hundred a year.
Really? Sure. Wow. It's
only a ship every three days
- And that's nothing.
And Well, it is funny
'cause now, you know,
if you think about it,
even Falcon 9 these days,
you're producing a second
stage about every two days.
Yeah. And a few years ago,
that would've been impossible,
you know, no one would've imagined
Yeah. That they're building an upper
- Stage.
And this year we'll make almost
200 upper stages of falcon.
- That's - Unbelievable. And
next year, probably over 200.
- That's
- So, so
- That's a cadence of people
I don't think are, you know,
just even, you can't even
imagine, you can't even fathom
that kind of, you know Yeah.
Output like that. That's
- Just crazy.
Well, Falcon 9 is, is
actually a heavy lift vehicle.
So, you know, it's,
there's roughly 40,000 pounds orbit.
Yeah. So,
which is in normal rocket
language would be a heavy lift.
Yeah. So now Starship's gonna be able
to do a hundred tons
orbit with Starship 2
maybe a little more than that
with Starship 3 like
at the 9 meter diameter, essentially,
when the nine meter diameter
is sort of fully stretched out
to what ends up being from
120 meters total length
to probably 140 or something like that.
Then it's lot, this is
like a lot of optimizations
and improvement engine improvements,
heatshield mass improvements,
reducing the amount
of propellant needed for landing, kind
of basically do all the things
that we've somewhat done
with the Falcon 9.
And you get to a pretty efficient vehicle.
I think we'll be able to do over 200 tons
to a useful orbit with Starship.
That's insane. So, and
that's with full reusability,
that's a full reusability,
which isn't Yeah.
Insane. So that's twice the Saturn V
with full reusability and
full and rapid reusability.
So it's the booster
and the ship are coming back
to the launch site. Right.
- Should we, should we take a look at,
at what's going on in there?
So, so as far as, you know,
we're seeing all this,
you know, you're talking about
even version one maybe be
able to do less than a hundred,
but is is version one really even gonna,
I feel like version one in my head
- Is just a, yeah.
Version one is a, is just
to the, the point of, and,
and really kind of Starship,
we're version 1.6 / 7, I don't know.
Right? Yeah. It's like we're,
we're like many iterations
through on, on version one.
Yeah. So,
- And it's just like
a, it's just a canvas.
It's like a, it's a test
experiment still at this phase.
It's just a, yeah. I don't
think people, they see it
and they don't understand that like,
this is all still a
giant test at this stage.
- Yeah. One way to look at
technology is to look at it as
like, you, you're rendering an image in
successive levels of detail.
So the first layer of the image is very,
very blurry and things are out of place.
And then with the, with the next pass,
it gets a bit more defined
and things kind of shift into
place and you do another pass
and another pass, and
eventually it's something
that is refined and,
and, and actually works.
Right. But we're, we're in
uncharted territory with,
with Starship, so it's not like
nobody's ever made a fully
reusable orbital rocket.
Right. And that's, that's really the,
the critical breakthrough
necessary for life
to become multi-planetary.
For us to become a true
spacefaring civilization, we have
to achieve full and rapid reusability.
Yeah. So I call it rapidly
reusable, reliable rockets.
- Reusable, RR squared or
R-R-R-R. Yeah. Yeah. Pirate
- Space
- Pirates.
There we go.
- So,
- And it's, the thing is that people need
to remember is getting, achieving
orbits in solved, I mean,
you guys have been getting
to orbit for a long time.
Course. Reusing
- It, solve, getting, I mean,
getting to orbit at all was
solved in the, in the fifties, right.
I mean, for, you know, so, so I mean,
I really don't think there's
another point in point in
another, an expendable rocket.
Right. In my opinion. So,
or at least I think the
math clearly demonstrates
that it is, there is no point
in a, in an expandable rocket,
you have to achieve re reusability.
We, we have reusability in
cars, we have in airplanes,
we have it in bicycles.
Horses, yeah. It's bizarre
to not have reusability in any other form
of transport boats.
It would be insane to like chuck a
boat away after every trip.
Right. But this is how rockets have worked
for the vast majority of time.
In fact, SpaceX is still
the only rocket that that is
has any reusability with Falcon 9.
Right. So with Falcon 9
we, we bring the boosters back.
We, we, we fly them frequently.
We bring the fairings
back, we refly those.
It's only the upper stage
that is expended right now.
It doesn't, Falcon 9 does not
qualify as rapidly reusable.
Right. Because the, the most
of the time the booster is landing on a
ship in the ocean. Right.
- So it takes a few days
to get it back. Yeah.
Oh, that's speeding up like crazy.
I mean, the cadence out of
the cape is unbelievable.
- Yeah. We're trying to
squeeze every like, quarter
of a knot that we can out of
the, the drone ships. Yeah.
- So seems that way.
- Yeah. We're, I mean, we're
jacking up the power on the
ships streamlining, streamlining them,
increasing the power on
the, the tugging vessels
so we could just haul ass
as quickly as possible.
- Well, yeah. I think you just
had your fastest turnaround
just last week.
There was a, I mean,
it was something like,
I don't remember the time, but it was
something like two days or something.
Yeah. From, from catching back
and then out to catch again
was just you know, insane.
It used to take so much longer. And yeah.
Those are all those little things
that people just aren't
necessarily paying attention to
that are continually improving and Yeah.
- No, the SpaceX Falcon
team is doing an incredible job
of achieving fast turnaround
reusability given the architecture.
Yeah. Now that's, that's still,
however, a couple days
to get a booster back
and then, you know, at least
a few days to refurbish it
for flight is still not rapid by aircraft
or, you know, vehicle, you know, and,
and like, take cars, boats, planes.
Right. You know,
doing a trip every four
days is not, would not Right.
Cut it in a car. Right,
right. Or an aircraft. Right.
So with, with Starship,
the booster comes back
to the launch site is caught
by, caught by the arms,
or, you know, this would
be quite spectacular Yeah.
To see giant mechazilla arms catching
a rocket in midair. Yeah.
And, and then those,
those arms put it back on the launch site.
So you can have the booster
back on the launch mount in,
well it's gonna come, it's gonna come back
and land in like five or six minutes.
Right. So,
so then you can probably get
it back on the launch site in,
well if you really push it,
you probably put get back on
launch site in 10 minutes.
Right. Or even five minutes.
And then you can fill it up
in half an hour.
So you could, you could be
ready to go an hour later
from the booster standpoint,
and then if you've got ships lined up,
you can drop another ship on,
you know, fill it with propellant.
And in theory you could be
launching every couple hours.
Yeah.
- It's hard to imagine now,
but it was hard to imagine
where Falcon 9 is today.
You know, 10 years ago no one would've
imagined what Falcon 9 is doing now.
So I I think time will
tell that, you know,
you can just keep
chipping away at all those
little improvements.
And so do you think you'll actually
- Fly?
Yeah, Falcon 9 used to be
have reusability measured in,
in months, then weeks,
then days, and then for,
but for Falcon 9, the
architecture is limited to you.
You really can't compress it
down less than several days.
Right. When you take
the landing out to sea
and then the necessary
refurbishment of the booster Yeah.
That is required. So
with, with, with Starship,
we'll take it from days to hours.
Wow. Do you think? And yeah.
And then, yeah, so then
there's the, the ship has to go
around the earth and,
and depending upon what
or orbit it has, it's
gotta have a ground track
that comes back over the launch site.
Right. So that could take
several orbits so it, the,
the ship could take,
you know, several hours,
sometimes half a day or something
like that to come back to re-align.
Yeah. Yeah. So you'd, you'd want
to have a lot more ships than boosters.
Yeah. So if you're really
going for max launch rate,
you probably want roughly,
I dunno, five ships
to for every booster. For every booster.
- Yeah. And that's what you
guys are building a pretty
massive cadence here of, of
ships and boosters already.
Yeah. Now do you think,
- Well, I mean, yeah, it's,
it's pretty slow compared to
what it will be like very slow.
But we're also iterating the design.
So like each one is a little
different from some cases,
a lot different from the last one.
Yeah.
- Are any of these, what, are any
of these gonna be the V2 yet?
Are we starting to get close
to V2 hardware yet, or?
Yeah,
- Just this, the, the stretch
version is basically V2.
Well, I guess it depends
on whether we call it V2
or don't call it V2.
The slightly stretched
version is V2 arguably.
That, so you can see, you know,
what we have here is a Starship
with, I've seen the heat,
the heat shield side and
the non heat shield side.
Yep. It's got the, what
we call the Pez dispenser
for tossing out the next
generation Starlink
satellites, the, the V3 satellites.
So those will be very wide
diameter like, like sort of,
I dunno, seven meter
diameter satellites.
Yeah. So, you know, 22 feet
or something like that. Right.
So,
- So are these actually gonna
be like, are we hoping to see
after, let's say this
test goes well tomorrow,
do you think the next one's
actually gonna go for orbit
and start deploying test, like testing out
as trying to deploy Starlink?
Or are we, where do you think
we're in, in that whole mix?
Like is that maybe a
few more down the road
to start actually deploying
payloads into orbit?
- We'll see how this mission goes.
I mean, this, this year is not,
not about delivering
satellites for Starship.
It's all about ironing out the, the,
the design question marks.
So the, I mean the major
things that remain to be solved
for Starship, the biggest, the, the,
the single biggest one is
what does it take to get
through the high heating of reentry?
So you can see the, the heat
shield that we have there.
We have some uh, well, let's say that
un unsolved questions Yeah.
On the heat shield. Yeah. A bunch
of which we don't even know
that they are questions.
And, and, and some we're aware of
because there've been
challenges in the past, like
with space shuttle Yeah.
The, the sort of the hinge
area and the hinge gap Yep.
And sealing that hinge gap
and not having hot gas just
go flowing super fast through,
through the, through the interface there.
Yeah. Through well at, at
where the flap hinge is. Yep.
'cause if, if, if you get hot
gas flowing through rapidly
that that'll cook anything Yeah.
Including the tiles. So, so you've,
you've got a,
you've got a hot gas
seal at the, the forward
and rear flap hinge.
And so, you know, one
of the key questions
is, does that seal work?
Right. We think it'll
work, but it may not work.
Then there are some, you
know, questions of like
how well do the tiles stay on.
Right. There's a, there's a
fundamental challenge here
where the tiles are ceramics,
they're very brittle,
they're like a, like a coffee cup Right.
Or a dinner plate. Yeah.
So you've got essentially a whole bunch
of dinner plates stuck to a steel surface.
The steel surface is
getting cryogenically cold
'cause of the propellants,
so it's shrinking.
Yeah. So on ascent, the,
the rocket is shrinking, it has shrunk.
Yep. So you got, you can't have the gaps
and the tiles be too tight
or they will just shatter
against each other.
Yeah. Yeah. The gap
will be too tight. Yep.
Then when it's coming in for
landing, the, the shuttle, the,
the, you no longer have the
cryogenic propellant in the main
tanks and the shuttles get,
the tiles get very hot.
Yep. So now they, they
want to expand. Yep.
So you've got a contracted inner surface
and expanding tiles.
Oh, geez. Yeah. Right.
So, and, and the thing is like, you can't,
you can't have a big tile gap
because then the plasma will get in there
and melt the primary structure behind it.
Exactly. Exactly. So like what's the,
what's the right tile gap?
And that's gonna vary depending
upon where you are on,
on the rocket on the ship.
Yeah. You know, so it's,
it's gonna be like some parts
of the ship have cryogenic
propellants, some don't.
Yeah. There's also the, how
well do the tiles attach
if we attach them and they,
and we accidentally break one.
But it's hard to see then
that that could be an issue.
Right. And we currently think we're,
we're probably not resilient
to failure of a, to loss
of a tile in the hot sections of the,
of the ship that are
the, the tank portion.
So that the, so if if
- The pressurized
- Areas Yeah.
The pressurized areas. Exactly.
So, and, and
so technically the nose
will be pressurized too.
So if the, if the
pressurized areas lose a tile
and then you melt that area,
that'll cause it to pop.
Right. Right. So the
ship will explode. Yeah.
So now people have asked like,
why are there some missing
tiles in the rear of the
- Ship?
Well, like right now, flight four,
you got I think three tiles
missing right now. Yeah. Yeah.
- So those are in the
rear of the, of the ship,
which is un pressurized region.
Yeah. Yeah. So that's an
un pressurized re region
where we think we can see, well you can,
you can have a melt through
of the un pressurized region
and it will not cause
failure of the, the vehicle.
Yeah. Yeah. Like you might have a
little hole there or something.
Right. But it's not gonna pop the vehicle.
- Right. So that's,
you're literally doing it
as like an A:B test almost
of like Yeah, we see
what happens if we're missing
- Tile.
Yeah. What happens if
you lose a tile? Huh?
Now we, we do have plans
for a secondary shield
beneath the tiles that is much
better than what we have right now.
So right now we, and some of the site
can't say the details of it
because it's like ITAR
control is sort of secret.
Right. But the current material we use,
we think is not resilient
to a tile failure.
We have a new design
that we think is resilient
to a tile failure.
- So behind the underlying structure.
- Yeah. And essentially it's got ablative.
So if you do, if you lose the
tile, you have to replace,
give your backup up the ablative.
Right, right, right. So you,
you, you'd have to, you'd,
you'd, you'd lose out on reusability
because of the lost tile
and the, and the ablative,
- But you have a, but
- At least it's intact. Yeah.
- And you'd recover it,
re refurbish it Yeah.
And get it back out on the
Yeah. On the fleet. That's
- Cool.
And especially for carrying
people, which ultimately we,
you know, expect Starship to carry it
maybe a hundred people at a time to Mars.
Right. And also to the moon. Yeah.
Then, you know, it's
gotta be super reliable.
It's gotta have no, no,
ideally no single point of failure. Right.
- So have you given up, I a long time ago,
you're talking about
transpirational cooling
or active regen and stuff.
Did that just kind of
didn't make the trade or
- I, - The mass trade that we
did, I think it's this point,
like it's four years ago
or something like that.
Yeah, maybe five.
It, it seemed like at that
time it would be at least twice
as heavy as a, a ceramic heat shield.
Now since then, the weight
of our ceramic heat shield has grown.
Yeah. And then when you factor
in the, the secondary shield,
that's additional mass.
Right. So, I don't know,
it may not be that big
of a difference between actively
cooling a heat shield and,
and having ceramic tiles.
- Have you seen what, what
Stoke Space out in Washington is
working on where they have a, it's
of course a aerospike's gonna
come, come outta my mouth.
'cause for some reason Aerospike
comes out every time
we talk about anything.
But it's a aerospike,
but the base plug is actually
the active region heat shield.
And so as it, and it's expander
cycle, so as it comes back
through the atmosphere, it's
actually, you know, heating,
they're using hydrogen to, to
actively regenerate, you know,
and cool the heat shield and
just gets dumped out the,
the nozzles basically as
it's, you know, as it's going.
And that actually also gets some
of the gaskets vented
out through the middle.
So you also have like a, a
boundary layer there too of,
of gaseous helium or hydrogen
in the, in the front.
And it's being actively regen.
I think it's, it's a
really cool, cool concept
and I was really impressed.
It's a, it's, it made me
just think about like regen,
you know, active regen in a different way.
And I thought that was pretty
neat. But I know you guys had
talked about the transpirational
cooling years ago, so it's,
I didn't know if Yeah,
- I think it's probably correct that that,
that a ceramic heat shield is gonna do
better than transpiration.
There's also the question of
like, if, if once if you go
to Mars and you're coming in
and, and hot and you're come
or you and you're coming back
to earth, you're coming in.
If you come back from, from Mars to earth,
you're coming in very hot.
Yeah, yeah. Yeah. It's not clear
where the transpiration
cooling could succeed
there. It came up there. Yeah.
- Your here's my wacky dumb
idea of the day is on the inside
of the tank, if you had
like a thermal camera,
you have like a fire hose
with cryogenic coolant,
just spray if there's a
hot a burn through Sure.
Spray it down from the inside.
I don't know, I'll just,
I'll always be happy
to throw out the dumb the dumb ideas.
Especially when you have
header tanks there, you know,
that are filled with, with
the cryo all pressurized ready
to go, you know, all
it's gonna take is one,
one heat shield tile missing potentially
and could have a Yeah.
A bad day. You know,
- There's a lot of ways
to solve the problem.
Yeah. So the, I mean,
what matters is that it is solved.
Yeah. Even though like, yeah, there are,
there are many ways to
achieve pool reusability.
What matters is that, is it is achieved.
- Yeah. A hundred
- Percent. And then bet
once you're in the sort of over
the hump of full reusability
where the one system is slightly
better than the other is a
secondary concern, right?
- Yeah. It's tomato, tomato
at that point. Yeah. Yeah.
Should we keep moving along here? Yeah.
So when, with flight three,
when it, when it broke up,
that was mostly just because obviously it
couldn't maintain
orientation, so it didn't
even have a chance of
- Having the heatshield.
Oh yeah. You would've
noticed that the engines,
there was a lot of like fire
coming from the engines area.
Just not, you know, that's not
good. Yeah, yeah. On reentry.
- Right. Definitely not when the
- Engines aren't on.
- Yeah. - So this is, you
can see we're just finishing,
we we're try to get the
shell completed as quickly
as possible, but we
still have a lot of work
to do on the interior of the factory.
But this will dramatically improve the
production of the rocket Yeah.
As being able to move from
one station to another,
which is a linear adjacent flow.
- Hmm. I don't, I mean, I assume,
I don't really know what that means, but,
- Well, I mean, the, the
thing that really matters for,
you know, people talk about
the moving production line
of sort of Henry Ford and the automobiles.
What actually matters is
linear adjacent flow as opposed
to a production line that moves
- Hmm.
So, so
- The, so it's, it's simple.
- Okay.
- Okay. Yeah. Like one thing leads one,
one step leads to another Yeah.
And it just, and things move
along in a cadence. Okay.
Yeah. Yep.
- And you don't have to have the physical,
- It doesn't matter whether
there's a convey belt
or not got, it's the secondary concern.
- That's the second. Yeah. Got
- It. Doesn't matter.
It just matters that, that,
that there's a, there's a tempo.
Yeah. So every station
has roughly the same
amount of work time.
Right. And things move from
one station to the next station
and the specialization
of labor at each station.
Yes. Okay. So these are the
principles that actually matter.
- And that's what you guys kind of
solved by doing the tents first.
'cause you could just
willy-nilly rearrange things, see
how things were actually falling, see
what order things were going in. But
- The tents were very inefficient
once you know what you wanna build. Yes.
- Yep. Yeah. So it was
the, your five step thing
of don't get too far along
in the automation before you
- Yeah.
You don't know what
you're gonna build. Yep.
Like it's simple to convey
just how, how much, like,
you know, this, this is, you
don't, we don't even know
what the rocket would look like.
- Yeah. Yeah.
- So,
- And in, in some senses you still
don't necessarily know it's still changing
- At this point.
We at this point we're confident of
that this architecture
will is is at least one
of the solutions.
Yeah. Let's not say there
couldn't be other solutions like
the one you talked about,
but that this will work.
Yeah. It's just a question
of ironing out the bugs
and improving the performance
of everything from the engines
to the avionics
to the primary structure,
the heat shield, everything.
Yeah. And
that's, but it will work.
Yeah. I think I was mentioning,
or I was beginning to say that the, the,
so the most important, the
toughest remaining problem is a,
a reusable orbital heat shield.
So there's never,
nobody's ever made it
reusable orbital heat shield.
So the space shuttle is the closest. Yeah.
But that took I think
something like nine months
and thousands of people to refurbish.
Right. So it's difficult to call when can,
can I call something that
requires so much work to refurbish
as truly re reusable?
Yeah. Certainly not rapid. Yeah.
So for the first time
ever, there needs to be a,
a rapidly reusable orbital heat
shield, which no one has ever done.
So it's a hard problem. Right.
So that's why I'd say
that's, that's the number one
biggest remaining problem.
And the, the, the goal of this flight,
and really the flights the, for
the rest of this year is get
through the high heating.
So the, the heat shield survives. Yep.
And, and then, and, and the,
the ship is still operational
and is able to steer
to a specific location
and do a landing burn Yep.
In the ocean. Yes.
And, and then the, the booster,
we wanted to be able to,
for this flight to come back
and do a landing boom
at a specific location.
Yep. So do we know, how
- Far out is that gonna be? Do you
- Know?
It's pretty far out. I mean, we're, but,
but I think we're pretty close to that.
If we don't solve it on this flight,
I think we'll solve it in, in
the next two or three flights.
So just having this, the,
the, the, the booster,
do the hot staging come back,
you know, do a boost back
steer, steer correctly and
to a precise location Yeah.
And do a landing burn and then, and, and,
and essentially do a
simulated tower catch. So it's
- Like, so will the tower actually
- No.
It's just a Okay. It, it, the
rocket will think it's Right.
Not trying to get caught
by the tower. Right.
- At least the, I thought it
would be kind of cool if the
tower mimicked it, you
know, out here to make sure.
Because I even wonder like
how do we know the tower's gonna be okay?
You know, like after a launch like that
to be able to Well we,
- We can, we, we operate the tower
after the launch so we can
tell if there's any damage.
Yeah. But yeah, if, if,
if this launch goes
perfectly we'll be able to,
we'll we'll have the, the,
the booster do a boost back
and a, a controlled aero
con, aero controlled descent
to a specific location.
Yes. Initiate landing, burn
and be caught by an imaginary tower.
Yep. Yep. And then the ship,
if things go perfectly,
which probably won't, it'll
get through high heating,
it will still be fully operational.
It will control itself
to a specific location
and in the ocean, and then
initiate a landing burn
and also pretend as to
getting caught by tower.
Wow. Now I think it, it,
I think we've got maybe a 50 50 chance
of the heat shield working. I mean
- That's decent.
- Yeah. Yeah. Like it's a
high, a high uncertainty,
but like roughly 50 50.
But if not on this flight,
it then in the next two
or three flights, I, I think
we'll solve that. Yeah.
- Well, and you guys, let's,
let's kind of head over here.
You guys did make a
decent amount of changes
to hopefully ensure
reentries better this time.
Like you added some new roll thrusters.
- Oh
- Yeah, yeah. And a few things like that.
- Well, yeah.
- What, what happened there
that the roll thrusters got,
because they got clogged it sounds like.
Yeah, yeah. Yeah. Don't
tell me that was the,
the old conversation we had
of hot gas thrusters and all that stuff.
Or was it, but still, I,
I'm still confused. 'cause
- They, they, they got ice,
ice, ice in the, in the valves.
- Okay. In the valves.
Not necessarily, or in the,
somewhere along the stream.
- They, they got clogged by
ice. We're not sure exactly how.
Yeah. But, but if water,
ice, we'll get into the, the,
the oxygen side, there's a small amount.
So since we're the location
that we're tapping off the
engine is not, is not pure O2,
it's got a little bit of a water ice.
- Why - Is that? It's, it's,
it's, it's ox rich gas.
- It is ox. So is it
coming off the actual Yeah.
Like exhaust or the
turbine side. Yeah. Really?
Yeah. So wouldn't it have,
- Wouldn't even have a little
bit of it's ox rich gas,
but it's Yeah, no, it's,
it's got burnt fuel.
- Yes. Wouldn't it have a little
bit of CO2 in it too then?
And can that turn into an ice?
Do you freeze CO2 with
that temperature? 'cause I think, yeah,
- Well anyway, it's, it's,
it's, it's, it's got stuff
that can turn solid at cryogenic
temperatures, the thing
that's relevant, right.
So
- Yeah.
Ice, whether it be water, ice or Yeah.
Or CO2 ice or whatever. Ice, ice.
- Yeah. And it's solid stuff
that does that. Blocks,
- Blocks things.
- Blocks things. So we do,
we we we've improved the sort of
ice strainers or the ice catchers.
Yeah. We improve the valves.
And something I think we'll
do in the future is move to,
for critical valves,
serious parallel valves.
So any one valve failure does
not, no matter what happens,
does not take out the ability of the ship
to orient itself correctly.
- So are you avoiding doing like a more
of a traditional heat
exchanger, like around raptor?
You know, like, like I think
Merlin probably does that,
where it has a heat exchangers
to heat up to be able to ride stuff.
The helium. Yeah. I'm just curious.
I've never heard of an engine
using like already combusted
to be able to be the
ullage gas, you know, off
of the, off the preburner.
That's pretty unusual I
think at least, I don't know.
- Yeah. Well we're,
our rocket is autogenously pressurized.
Yeah. So we're pressurizing the
fuel side with gaseous fuel.
Yep. And the oxide with
mostly gaseous oxygen. Yep.
And yeah.
Now in the case of
autogenously pressurized,
we have to create the gas.
We're not merely warming up a gas.
We have to produce the gas.
- Oh, interesting. Is that how
the shuttle did it too then?
'cause the shuttle ran
on the RS-25's had
autogenous pressurization on
- The, on the hydrogen side.
Yeah. I think that it, I,
- Well I guess I don't
know if it's on both.
- Was it on both? I
don't know. I don't know.
I think it was at least
on, on the hydrogen side.
So maybe on both.
But when, when you, when you
have autogenous pressurization,
you've gotta produce the gas.
You're not just heat it up. Okay.
So there's a lot more mass
you better come up with Yeah.
- Literally.
- Yeah.
It actually affects our max power on the,
especially on the fuel side.
So the fuel pump has to
work well, both pumps have
to work harder, but the fuel pump
especially is a limiting factor.
Like if we turned off autogenous
pressurization on the fuel
side, we'd actually be able to get
more power out of the fuel pump.
- Oh yeah. 'cause you're
having to drive all that.
- Yeah. You've gotta, you've
gotta gas that you're, you're,
you're, you're bleeding mass flow right.
From the, you know, from the
engine. Yeah, from the engine.
Yeah. You're,
and yeah, I mean there's,
there's quite a lot of work in,
in taking a cryogenic liquid
and heating it up to be a hot gas.
Right. So you're a phase
transition and, and,
and that big temperature delta.
Yeah. So it's actually a, a lot of work
to produce the hot gas
from a cryogenic liquid.
- That's crazy. So is that
what also, can we, can we kind
of step in here and see
the, all the boosters?
This is crazy.
Is that what also was the blockage
of the LOx tank on the booster too then?
Similar ice buildup, blockage?
Or was it on flight three?
The Raptors were shutting
down during boost.
Backburn had an ice buildup.
Is it a similar thing to that?
- Sorry, it's hard to hear you.
- Yeah. Is that what
caused the, the booster
to shut down on flight three
with the ice ice buildup?
Was it a similar type of thing?
Like an autogenous pressurization issue
that clogged a few of the engines?
- Yeah. We didn't have enough
pressure to start the engines.
- Okay. - So we're low low
pressure start the, the, the,
the full answer is quite complicated.
But because arguably we
could have started with
with lower pressure or we, we didn't need
to start all the engines anyways.
This, this time we expect
to have a lot more pressure
and we are able to start at lower pressure
and we don't need to have
all the engines fire.
Okay, cool. You know, hopefully. Yeah. So,
- Geez, this is crazy.
Wow. The scale is just almost impossible
to to imagine. And
- Yeah, three, three boosters.
- Wow. That's just insane.
This looks so cool.
- Dang.
- Lot of engines.
- Yeah. It's an insane amount of engines.
I mean, right here we're
looking at what, 99 Yeah.
Engines for these three vehicles.
Nine ounces. Nine nines.
- Nine, nine Raptors on a wall.
- 99 engines and a ship ain't one. Yeah.
That's absolutely insane.
The scale of these things, it's just hard
to, hard to fathom.
Wow. So are you guys
are trying to move down
to three grid fins, is that right?
From the, from the four Is that
- It's sort of high priority.
It's a, it's a mass
optimization to move you,
you definitely only need three.
Yeah. And I think technically
you could do it with two
if you're willing to oscillate
- Yeah.
Like turn for yard, then road
roll again for pitch and Yeah.
- That's definitely, you
know, you're asking for a bit
of trouble if you just have two grid fins.
Right. But it is
technically possible. Right.
The three three for sure.
But that's, that's like
a, that's a fairly minor
optimization, right.
- With the, the, the cowbell
diverter things, you know, the,
the ullage gas thrusters or whatever.
I need to clear something up for myself
because I'm getting confused.
So cold gas thruster, we'd say like,
would be like a nitrogen thruster
where it's just literally compressed
nitrogen goes out of an nozzle.
- Cold gas is room temperature gas usually
- Is room temperature.
And then are we, would we consider
that almost like a warm gas
- Thruster? Yeah. Warm gas thruster.
- And then like a hot gas
would be where it's a reaction.
Probably like a bi a bi
propellant thruster still
- For both the booster and the ship.
You don't really need much control.
The attitude control needed is, is small.
So you just can't have a leaky valve
or a stuck valve [or a stuck Valve].
- Yeah. That seems, I I,
this is like the third time we've
- Falcon 9s, is all cold gas.
- What is
- Falcon 9s all cold gas.
And we've done, I think six starts.
So it's, it's, it's cold gas that has been
maintaining propellant settling
and attitude control for,
you know, 12 hours. Right?
- Yeah. So, and you
have a lot of it on tap.
So that's, I don't know why
that's still a hard one for me to fathom.
Even though we've talked,
this is the third time
- Now its got a lot of hot
gas. Yeah. Or warm gas,
- Especially when it's empty.
It's, it's all warm, warm gas. Yes.
- The, the delta delta
V needed is tiny. Yeah.
So it's very tiny
thrusters are needed. Ah.
So yeah.
- So how much do you feel like
after you fly, how much is
it like, oh God, we have
to change all of these?
Like is it, is it literally
you find something on one
and then you're literally
like in immediately having
to make changes on all these things?
Like everything that's
in production? Yeah.
- You're just learning lessons.
There's, there's hundreds
learning changes that actually take place.
Not a few, yeah. Hundreds.
If you go to a detail level,
there might be thousands
of changes that happen,
- Especially when you get
software involved. I'm sure it's
- Software for sure.
I'm just taking a, talking
hard. It's hardware.
If you're just, look, the
hardware changes across the ship
and the, the booster
and the engines, it's thousands
of changes between each flight.
But many of them are very small.
But a very small change
could be a big deal.
- Imagine how long it'd take a
traditional aerospace company
that had a, a rocket they're working on
to make a thousand changes between flights
and then fly it two months later.
I mean that's, that's
what we're doing here.
This is, you're barely over
two months from the last flight
and the vehicle's had
over a thousand changes
- Easily.
Over a thousand, several thousand
probably. So that's insane.
- Like - You said, a bunch
of 'em, a little changes,
but say like, is it
different in a way that could
have a, an effect on the rocket?
Yeah. Yeah. That's
probably several thousand.
- And do you feel like for now,
are you generally like kind
of overbuilding them to just
try to get through the point
of being able to prove the heat
shields prove all the stuff
and then eventually you're work on
- Mass?
Yeah. We're, we're trying
to answer the questions
that I mentioned.
The biggest question being
can, what does it take
to get through max heating?
Yep. With a reusable heat
shield, then being able
to have the booster come back
and be caught by the, the tower Yep.
And have the, the ship also come
back and be caught by the tower.
Yeah. So those are the three very big
things that need to happen.
- And that's in your mind
when you're launching these,
including like flight 1, 2, 3,
you're, those are the questions.
Like those flights are just
to answer bonus questions
- Full reusability.
- See I think people just
don't understand that that's,
you're not looking at
trying to get out there and,
and launch a satellite tomorrow.
You're trying to answer the
- Questions.
The payload, the payload for
all the flights this year is
data is data just to learn things.
So it's, it's design refinement
to understand what actually,
what, what works, what doesn't work.
Yeah. You know, some things
sometimes work Right.
Which can throw you off
'cause it worked once,
but doesn't work again
because of the combination
of factors isn't the same.
Yep. So, so you want to have, so
the first things you'll find
are like fundamental errors
of design where success was not
one of the possible outcomes.
Yep. Then in some cases it's
kinda like Russian roulette
success is sometimes possible.
Possible, right? Yeah. But once in a while
you, you blow yourself up.
Yeah. Yeah. So that's gonna
require a lot of flights to,
to figure out those like
the, the one in 10 failure,
the one in a hundred
failure, that kind of thing.
Yeah. There'll be a whole
bunch of things like that.
- Well, kind of even like the
SN stuff when 8 was darn
close to landing 9 was
almost a reversion feeling.
10 was better, 11 was worse.
Like there's a little bit of a
ping pong as things were kind
of being tried and tested.
And you're still kind of in that phase.
Even even at this scale.
I just don't think people
are used to that. You know?
- Yeah. I mean a lot, a lot of
those like early tests were,
were also just about us
learning how to work with
stainless steel Right.
As the primary, primary
structural element. Yeah.
And working with liquid methane. Right.
And with a, a full flow stage
combustion engine. Right.
As the, as the engine. Yeah.
So a lot of what people saw
was that the, the, the flight,
you know, did it land or not land,
but we're just trying to
figure out how do we work
with steel Right.
And how do we work with a
methane as a fuel and a new
- Engine architecture
- And a
totally new engine architecture
- And new flaps. Like
things that are just Yeah.
- Do the flaps
- New and novel.
- Yeah. You have to actuate the flaps.
You need, you need very powerful
actuators for the flaps.
Yeah. 'cause there are a
lot of force. It's like an
airplane moving its wings.
- Right, right. So
- These are very powerful
actuators that are needed.
- Yeah, absolutely.
- So, you know,
and all of the, the the,
like the, the engine
to vehicle interactions
are very complicated.
Yeah. So, but you,
you don't really see those
on the test stand when you,
when you're firing the
engines on the test stand,
you don't get the engine
to vehicle interactions.
And then you've got different Right.
Engines vehicle interactions in
flight than you do on the ground.
- Yeah. Oh a hundred.
Especially when you're changing
orientation of a vehicle.
Yeah. And different G-Force
and zero G mean all the things
- There, there's no test
stand that can test a,
a rocket at 17,000 miles
an hour doing six Gs Right.
In, you know, every
different orientation. Right.
Exactly. It's not, it's not possible. Yep.
- So you have to fly it.
- Yeah. You, you do as much
as you can on the ground,
then you gotta fly it, try
to figure things out in simulation.
But a lot of things are not gonna
be included in the simulation.
So it'll work in some, but not in reality.
- Exactly. It's crazy.
Shall we keep moving?
- Yeah,
- Sure.
- Are you
- I
over here that way?
Yes sir. We are just about
to de-rig from the crane and then
- Right on.
- Geez.
- Wow.
- Are we good down there? Yep.
- As you can see, the Raptor is a
lot cleaner than it used to be.
It looks like this less stuff, but Yeah.
- That
- Already.
- Yeah.
- But these, these are still not like the,
we're not to V3 here yet, right? No,
- No.
- Is the V3 the same thing
as like the Leet (733T) engine?
Is that, are those
- Sort of the LEET engine
was, I think we will do
that at some point, but that's like a,
that's really a total tear up.
Really. Yeah. Yeah.
It looks like the LEET engine,
but it's way more expensive
because it still has
printed parts, for example.
So, but the, yeah,
the next gen Raptor engine
needs no heat shield.
- Right.
- So,
- And because it's exposed,
it has to have cooling.
So there's integral
cooling circuits throughout
the, all the parts.
So it looks very simple on the
outside, but it's complicated on the
- Inside.
Like even all throughout the,
like the preburner and the Yeah.
Gas manifolds and everything. It's all,
- All that stuff you see
stuck on the side disappears.
- Wow.
- And that's actually, you like
that's being worked on now
already. That's already,
- Yeah.
We have a design, we have a
design that that, that works.
It, it, it, it looks like
the engine isn't complete.
- Well yeah, you had that,
that that render on the,
that presentation it just
looked like literally
like a, it looks
- Like it's missing
- Parts mock up. Yeah. Yeah.
- But it's actually just
the, the secondary circuits
and integral cooling are
part of each part, so Wow.
So if you have a
secondary cooling circuit,
you run the secondary cooling circuit or,
or secondary flow circuit
through the various parts.
Right. And we also eliminate
a whole bunch of bolted
and welded joints.
So especially the bolted
joints, you really wanna
get rid of those. Yeah,
- Yeah.
- You know,
- Bolts and flanges
and seals of hell,
especially if they're hot.
So Yeah. The, the next gen Raptor engine
is actually a little difficult to service
because there are parts that are,
that don't have a flange anymore,
it's just welded shut. Right,
- Right, right.
Yeah. So you're just hoping to
be able to get the design up
to be so reliable, hopefully
that Yeah, you just don't need a service
- Result.
You need to change the part, you need to
literally cut it open.
- Wow. So you'll probably,
at this point you might
as well just like swap out the whole
engine, I assume and just ah,
- No, we cut it open. Yeah,
- Yeah,
- We got it open.
- Alright. It's just crazy. Yeah.
- I mean there's a massive,
massive bolted flange
for the hot gas manifold that's
transferring hot gas from
the .
Hot, hot from the fuel pump
side. Yeah. You can see that
- Three,
- It's, it's, well it's hard to point at
'cause it's up in the air, but the thing
that joins the, the, the, the
- Fuel the ox. Yeah. The fuel to
- Pump to the ox
- To pump, yeah.
The kind of band looking thing.
- Right. Yeah. The band
looking thing that, that's a,
that has a, a mon, a monster
flange at the top and bottom.
Mm. And you want to get rid of those two
- And that has to hold a lot of pressure.
- Hot. That's a whole lot of
pressure. Lot of pressure. Yes.
- Geez.
- I mean you can see
there's a lot of flanges here.
I mean this valve is like, well
this, this pump is like made
of flanges Wow.
Flange, flange flange, flange flange
- And are, and like,
- I mean these are
beast beast level flanges
- And these are all there.
So there is no like, active
cooling inside of two like this
or the current version of
Raptor like this. There's no
- Current version.
Does not have, there's,
there's no, there's no, well
there technically is some,
but there's not, the current version
of raptor does not have
sufficient cooling to be able to
resist being in the, in hot gas plasma.
Hot plasma. Yeah. It's not, yeah, it
- Would melt.
That's why I need, that's still
why I need the shield here
- Then.
Yeah. That's why it's,
it's heavily shielded.
But next gen, a bunch
of the flanges you see here will disappear
and it will have integral cooling
and integral secondary flow circuits.
Yeah.
- Yeah. Do you guys look,
is it possible to do a,
- There's a whole bunch of engines down
there pretty densely packed.
It's a lot of thrust.
- It's a lot of thrust. It is crazy.
It looks like a, when you go
to a Christmas street store
or something just, yeah, that's insane.
- Each one of these is the most
advanced rocket engine ever made
- And they're just being
cranked out like it's nothing.
- Yeah. Super high pressure, high
efficiency you've got a full flow stage.
Combustion all the good.
It's insane. Yeah.
- Is there, is there ever been
any look into, like, I know,
you know, with aircraft
turbines you can do, you know,
like some kind of cooling on
the actual turbine blades.
Is there any way to do any kind
of cooling on the turbine blades and,
- And Raptor, we've, we've had
that discussion many times.
We probably head back into the,
and see the main factory.
- Geez. I just can't believe
how much has changed out here.
You have two mega bays.
I mean, last time I was out
here there was only one mega bay
and it's neither nothing had doors.
Now you have doors.
That's a pretty good creature comfort.
It is turning into a real
factory, you know, it's, yeah.
Well this is a real factor
that we're building here. Yeah.
- So
- Quite big.
It's hard to keep up
with everything out here.
- Yeah. So this is a, we'll
finally have a real factory
for Starship, not just making it in tents.
Yeah. So long term we
wanna try to get the thrust
of Raptor up to around
330, maybe a little higher,
maybe 335 metric tons.
So that'll take us to a 10,000
ton thrust at lift off.
- That's absolutely absurd.
Sorry. That's absurd. Yeah.
Yeah. It's absurd. Like beyond absurd.
That's coming up on three times the
amount of powers of Saturn V.
- That's, yeah, that'd
be roughly three times.
So Saturn five. Yeah,
- That's what you need. Like
- 22 million pounds
of thrust Saturn five
is seven and a half. Oh
- My gosh.
- So
- Absolutely insane.
Well, and I think, you know,
there's this kind of feeling of
why aren't we, aren't people
doing things like the,
you know, the Saturn V being built in
the, you know, in the
- Sixties, Saturn V is
primitive compared to Starship.
- Yes. And it's insanely
expensive. It wasn't sustainable.
- Yeah. And it was, it was expendable.
So yeah, Starship is in a,
I mean, just any rocket
that is fully reusable,
which no one has achieved because
it is extremely difficult.
Not because they didn't think about
- Reusability. Right. Right.
- So it was just too hard.
So, and obviously we haven't
achieved that either.
You know, we, we've gotta,
I'm hopeful that we'll achieve
achieve it by next year.
So, but at least, at
least we have a situation
where we have a design
where success is one of
the possible outcomes.
Yeah. So no, no prior design
where success is one of the possible
outcomes for full reusability.
- Well, and if you think
about it, let's say you guys
for some reason just were
like, okay, screw it.
We have to launch 300
metric tons to orbit.
You could absolutely, you could.
You could expend a rocket if you like.
Absolutely had to for some reason. Yeah.
- It be pointless.
- It would be pointless.
But like you have that capability
like for the first time.
Oh yeah. Since this added five.
- Well, I mean generally if
you can do 200 tons reusable,
you can do double that expendable. Right.
- 400 tons. Yeah. Yeah.
Which is insane. Yeah.
I mean, even to the point
of if you had to do,
let's say you had to do, you know, HLS
or something to try to
speed it up or something
and you know, if orbital
refuelings not done or something,
- No orbital re refilling, I
mean, I don't wanna count check
before they hatch, but, or
orbital re refilling is really
just docking with ourselves.
Yeah. We dock with the space
station all the time. Right.
A space station is way harder
to dock with than ourselves.
- And but will it be all docking
up to a, to like a depot?
Is that kinda the plan?
Is there to be an orbital?
It depends on how
- Quickly you wanna launch.
So if you, if you're gonna
the moon, I don't know.
I don't think you need a de depot.
I think you just send a ship up
and send tankers immediately.
Yeah. And your boil off rate
will not be too bad. Okay.
So you now for the moon,
you'd want to have a dedicated
earth orbit to moon system
because you don't need a heat shield.
Right. Well I need a heat
shield to brake I suppose.
Well, prob probably actually. Yeah.
The, the moon's like harder than it seems
because it doesn't have an atmosphere.
Right. So you can't use the
atmosphere to brake. So,
- But if you have time
- You can, I guess you probably
have anyway.
It's like yeah, for landing on the moon,
obviously you don't need
flaps, don't need heat shield
and you need very little thrust.
Right. But you do need
pretty big landing legs.
So in case you one leg lands on a boulder
and one lands on a crater.
Absolutely. And you don't wanna tip over.
- Right. So
Because that's a, you know, I
think HLS, I don't think a lot
of people understand that
we're going from a 16 tonne lunar
lander with the Apollo
program to a, you know,
I mean I don't even know how heavy HLS is
gonna be when it, when it lands.
It's gonna be at, you know,
at least 10 times that massive
and or wait Yeah.
At least 10 times that massive
and acres of volume compared to anything
that was landed during the Apollo program.
And I just think that people
aren't necessarily ready for
how, how big Starship will be on the moon.
It's basically a habitat when
it's on the moon, you know,
it's not just a little tiny
tent like the Apollo lunar landers.
Yeah.
- Yeah. I mean I think
the, the next step is to go
beyond Apollo and have a permanently
occupied base on the moon.
Yeah. Like Moon base alpha,
that's the next step.
So you don't wanna just
have a few people there
for a few hours who wanna have
a permanently occupied base.
Right.
- This factory's huge. Yeah.
This, and I guarantee we
came back in a year, it'd be
just up and running like
a normal factory already.
- I mean it'll be, this will be filled
with equipment in three months.
- Geez. So is there a decent
amount of like, new stuff
that's like, is there
hardware coming in here
and tools that are coming here
that will unlock like Yeah,
just mostly production rate
or even like new ideas or,
or what's that kinda like?
- I mean, you can build any
given design in an artisanal way
slowly with, you know, by having
a lot, a lot of crews come
to the same station, but in
order to have real production,
you've gotta move from one
station to another where
you have the same amount
of work at each station.
Right. So this is meant
to have a lot of stations.
So you'll see a lot of work in Yeah.
And you'll be able to
see very clearly, I guess
where the, where the blockages are
- And make changes to it then.
Yeah.
- Geez.
- It's so funny to think about how, I
know we were only five years
ago out here when the MK1
and all you had was a tent
and Stargate was the
biggest thing out here.
That little Stargate thing. Yeah.
And now you, I almost missed it trying
to pull into Stargate today 'cause
- It looks like a little hut.
- Yeah. It's like dwarfed
by absolutely everything
else out here already.
Yeah. It's just crazy.
Oh, that feels nice.
- Air conditioning.
- Holy crap. It just keeps going. Yeah.
I thought that was the main thing.
- Yeah. Geez. It was more
behind that wall. Yeah.
- Holy crap.
So this is more of a, a real factory here.
This is what the other side will
- Look like.
Yeah. The other side will look like this.
You know, there were, we're
obviously just checking each
tile to make sure it's not
cracked and it's well seated.
- How are you feeling about the,
the way they're actually secured on there?
Like the, the mounting point? Is that
- Decent?
We're continuing to iterate
on the mounting point.
- I always, I
- Mean it's, it has a, you know,
99% of the time it works well.
So it's just a question of
figuring out what are the 1% that
have issues with cause
cause the tile to crack
or some other problem.
- I always keep thinking the,
the one of the big challenges
that you can't access the,
you can only access it.
You can't access it
from either side really.
Like there's not a bolt you can screw on
because you have, it's a snap-on.
It's a, it has to be a snap-on. Yeah.
Have you ever seen the
like furniture mountings
where like you have two
pieces of wood joined together
and then you spin a magnet on one end?
Oh yeah. And it spins the nut on.
I've always wondered like if
something like that could be,
- I mean this is basically, it snaps on
and you pretty much have to
break the tile to pull it off.
- Really? Yeah.
- Huh. That's meant to go on and stay on.
- Yeah. And we still see,
like even on the, the parts
that aren't tapered up, you
know, like on the main's body,
we still see some, some horizontal seams.
What's the, what's the
deal with those seams?
I know that was like pretty bad.
- No, they, they don't
really matter that much.
They're just different
sections of the nose cone.
So now
this is somewhat of a debate.
You could wait until the whole
nose cone is made and then,
and then put the attachment
points on at that point.
So currently we put the tile attachment
points on in sections.
Okay. So that's why you've got a line, the
- Horizontal line.
Okay. Yeah. It's probably
just a lot harder to,
once it's all manufactured,
it's so massive it'd be hard
to put all the attachment points on.
Is that kind of the problem
- There?
There's more one way to skin a cat.
This is just a cat getting skinned. Yeah,
- Yeah.
- Yeah. It's not, it's not to say
that there is not a better way to do it.
Yeah. There are.
The first order of business is
to get one way at all That works.
Yep. Thereafter to optimize. Yep.
- Hmm.
- Watch your step here.
- There's still a lot
of work that we gotta do here.
- Oh, that's cool looking.
That's, is that the, the
landing tank for Yeah,
- It's the header tank.
- Header tank there. That's insane.
Geez. And then are those COPVs propped
up against it like that then?
Is that what those Yeah. Geez.
- Gotta pressurize the head attack with
something when the engine's not on.
- Exactly. Wow.
So the, like the Pez door
that we see on Starship now is
that, do you think
that's gonna stick around
or is there still gonna be like a
chomp or someday? Or is it
- Well, for the Starlink satellites,
they're pretty flat. So
- The chomper makes sense.
- There's no point in having
a giant fairing for a,
you know, flat little,
it's a giant flat pancake.
Right.
- What did the, the door test
go reasonably well on the last
one, or, because I think
you guys aren't doing
anything with it had some issues.
Yeah. It's pretty rudimentary
of course, I assume.
- Yeah. But it's, well
that you've got this sort
of really quite sophisticated
factory on a sandbar.
On a sandbar by the
Rio Grande. Yeah. Yeah.
It's like an alien
spaceship landed. Right.
- Seriously. So these are,
are these thrusters here then?
Yeah. Is that what these are
- Little, little old jet packs.
This will take the detailed stuff of the,
that might run a foul and ITAR stuff
- Deal.
- Yeah. I mean, I don't know if,
if anyone is gonna copy us, that would be,
that's a hard thing to copy.
- It's come a long way since three tents.
Yeah, it sure has. I mean,
everything's clean in this.
There's no mud and dust. It's better when
- It's has doors on it.
Yeah.
- I mean, everything used
to have mud and dust. Yes.
And birds and things.
- There's only some finite mud and dust,
but it's much smaller
- Than, it's a long ways from
- MK1.
Yeah. Yeah.
I mean the MK1 thing,
it looked like the junk yard at Tatooine
- Which was charming.
Yeah.
- It was a lot of dust
and mud. Farside rocket.
- Yeah.
- The bar, the farside rocket.
I mean, MK1 was conceptual
as a concept piece. Yeah.
Concept, I'd say concept art. It was
- Part of the journey.
Absolutely. Yeah.
So James pointed out that the,
this actually wraps
all the way around the,
like all of that's still back there.
There's more to it.
Yeah. That's coming down.
That's the dome line.
Jeez. That's the dome line.
Dome line and the coils.
That's the starting line's
over there. That's crazy.
- Yeah. So we do have an
existing factory that's wrapped
around the one you just saw.
So that's, that's where we make the,
the ship and the booster. So then
- That will open up and you'll start Yeah.
Serpentining it basically through there.
- Yeah. Look that we'll
take down that wall there.
That is, once we have the
doors on the other side,
we will take down that wall
and then you'll just have factory.
We'll just kind of go as
far as the eye can see.
- It's so much bigger than
I thought from the road.
I mean, it looks big from the road,
but it's insane. Yeah, it's
- Ridiculous.
And obviously the, the, the
sections get gradually bigger
as, as you go south, right?
So that's why things
start off sort of short
and then get taller as you go along
- Even.
Yeah. Even the roof line does that, right?
- Yeah. It's gonna get bigger
if the pieces get bigger.
- That's absolutely crazy.
Are you guys still using,
like, I, I remember, you know,
back in the day there's a lot
of like Tesla motors being used.
Oh, ac actually you said that
way it out that way. Okay.
So there's a lot of Tesla motors
being used, like, you know,
to, for the fins and all that kinda stuff.
And maybe even the grid
fins had like literally a
Model S motor or something.
Are you still kind of using
some Tesla parts like that?
- Yeah, we just use the Tesla drive units
to actuate the grid fins
- And, and the big flaps still too.
The on ship.
- Yes. Sorry. Two. Yes. Essentially.
Sorry, I was just thinking
about something else.
Yeah, the, the, the
- Hey,
- The, yeah.
We use the, we're we're
trying not to use hydraulics.
We're trying, it's all
electric actuation. Yeah.
So the engine is
also gambled electrically.
- Yep. So you're really moving away from
hydraulics wherever, possibly. Really?
- Yeah. There's almost,
I think there's actually no
hydraulics in the vehicle.
I, if there's hydraulics
some very tiny little part,
huh. But I think there's none.
- That's wild. Actually. I
can't even think of another.
- Yeah, there's pneumatics,
- Right?
A lot for all the valves and
everything obviously. Yeah.
That's crazy.
- Geez.
- It's surreal compared to what it was.
Yeah, it was surreal just
a little bit ago. Wow.
It just keeps going and going. That is
- Crazy.
Yeah. From one little tent. Yeah.
- This is starting to make Hawthorne look
tiny. And Hawthorne's a,
- A big, well, Hawthorne's
actually a whole campus.
Cool. Absolutely crazy.
- That's Meme Street.
- Meme Street? - yeah.
Is that, is that what it says now?
- That's what, that's what it's called.
- All right. I think we're
jumping in a different car here.
- But if you look at the street sign
- We got Meme Street. Yeah. It's
- Literally called Meme Street.
It's, that is its official
name. It used to be called Wemes.
And we changed it from Wemes to Memes.
- The important things.
I love it. Holy crap.
Was that incredible or what?
Huge Thank you to especially
Elon Musk for showing us around
and, and following up and,
and just teaching us so
much about what's going on
and, and showing us the inside.
Huge thanks. Amazing.
And I also owe a huge thank
you to our supporters,
especially those over on Patreon.
If you wanna support the
work we do here, head on over
to patreon.com/everydayastronaut,
and now is a great time to be a supporter
because we already have
part two up for review.
So again, patreon.com/everydayastronaut
to catch part two right now.
But even if you're not a supporter,
fear not part two is coming
out once reviews are done.
So be sure you're subscribed
so you don't miss out.
And while you're waiting a good free way
to support the channels to
just watch some recent videos
that you might have missed,
like other tours of companies
or deep dives on
alternate launch concepts.
So click around, watch a few.
It truly helps the channel out.
And while you're online, be sure
and check out our awesome merch
store for shirts like this,
our new orbital shirt and lots
of other incredible things
over everydayastronaut.com/shop.
Thanks everybody. That's
gonna do it for me.
I'm Tim Dodd, the Everyday
Astronaut, bringing space down
to earth for everyday people.